{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This 2005 inductee into the Nevada Writers Hall of Fame escaped the Paiute War by traveling to Virginia City and San Francisco to perform on stage as part of “A Paiute Royal Family.” This author wrote an 1883 work, subtitled Their Wrongs and Claims, in an effort to raise monetary support for their people and to challenge ethnic stereotypes. The author of Life Among the Piutes, which is considered the “first autobiography written by a Native American woman,\" and representing Nevada in the National Statuary Hall, for ten points, who was this author and activist?",
      "answer": [
        "Sarah Winnemuca or Sarah Hopkins",
        "or Thocmentony",
        "or Tocmetone"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This city is home to the medieval Merchant's Bridge, the longest-inhabited bridge in the world, and an 1808 meeting in this city, between Alexander the First and Napoleon Bonaparte, forced Sweden to join the Continental System. Henry the Sixth called a meeting in this city to resolve a dispute between Louis the Third and Archbishop Conrad of Mainz that ended in disaster. An 1184 building collapse in Thuringia led over sixty nobles of the Holy Roman Empire to drown in human excrement in a latrine disaster in, for ten points, what German state capital city?",
      "answer": [
        "Erfurt",
        "Erfurt Latrine Disaster and similar answers",
        "Congress of Erfurt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person, whose government proposed the \"Kaldor Budget,\" wrote \"The West on Trial,\" a work concerning their efforts toward national independence. This co-founder of the Political Affairs Committee called for a strike against the Booker Sugar Company and was arrested after the Royal Welsh Fusiliers arrived. This person's wife, Janet Rosenberg, worked with Forbes Burnham and this leader to found the People's Progressive Party. The first ethnically Indian head of government outside of the Indian subcontinent, for ten points, who was this president of Guyana?",
      "answer": "Cheddi Jagan or Cheddi Berret Jagan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Justin the Second's failed siege of this city precipitated his mental breakdown, and this city was called \"The Shield of the Empire\" by Ammianus Marcellinus, for its resistance of a Persian siege. This city was the capital of the province of Mesopotamia under Diocletian, and Dara was fortified by Anastasius in order to serve as a counter to this city in modern-day Turkey. For ten points, identify this Roman citadel, which was turned over to the Persians after the death of the Roman emperor known as Julius the Apostate.",
      "answer": [
        "Nisibis or Nusaybin",
        "or Nesbin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was mentored by George Washington Gale, the founder of the Oneida Institute of Science and Technology, and this man banned slave owners from Communion at the Chatham Street Chapel in New York City. This husband of the New York Female Moral Reform Society founder, Lydia Root, succeeded Asa Mahan as president of Oberlin College and taught students like Theodore Weld. For ten points, name this Presbyterian Minister and \"Father of Old Revivalism\" who led the Second Great Awakening.",
      "answer": "Charles Grandison Finney 1 2023-24 HS National History"
    },
    {
      "question": "This site was the largest adobe city in the Western Hemisphere and is known for its ciudadelas [[syoo- dah-DEH-lahs]]. This site contains the high walled compound of Nik An, in which reliefs of fish represent the Humboldt Current and El Niño [[NEE-nyoh]]. Situated in the Moche [[MOH-cheh]] Valley, near the modern- day city of Trujillo [[troo-HEE-yoh]], this city was conquered by the Incas in 1470. For ten points, name this archeological site, which served as the seat of the Chimú Empire in western Peru, the largest city in pre- Columbian South America.",
      "answer": [
        "Chan Chan",
        "Chimor before \"Chimu\" is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person gives their adopted name to the county seat of Caledonia County in Vermont, and one work by this person was inspired by their experiences in Chester, New York. This person popularized the Latin motto \"Ubi panis ibi patria,\" in one context, and praised the \"fair cities, substantial villages, extensive fields\" of middle colonies in a work that notably described the American frontier to European audiences. For ten points, name this French-American author of a set of Letters from an American Farmer.",
      "answer": "John Hector St. John"
    },
    {
      "question": "Difficulty traversing the Flossgraben canal presented a challenge for one side at this battle, where Dodo von Knyphausen crossed the Via Regia. The Heilbronn Alliance was formed in the aftermath of this battle, in which a cavalry charge was led by Pappenheim before he was mortally wounded. Axel Oxenstierna took the reins of a war effort in the aftermath of this 1632 battle, following the death of \"the Lion of the North\". For ten points, name this battle of the Thirty Years' War in which Gustavus Adolphus was killed.",
      "answer": "Battle of Lützen"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city, home to the Lala Mustafa Pasha Mosque, was nicknamed the \"city of 365 churches\" and was given one of its early names by Ptolemy the Second, referencing his sister, Arsinoe [[ar-SIN-noh-ee]]. A 1571 siege of this city ended with the flaying of Venetian officer Marco Antonio Bragadin, who defended this city from a much larger Ottoman force, potentially facilitating victory for the Holy League at Lepanto. For ten points, name this city, located east of Nicosia, a major port city in the medieval period of Cyprus.",
      "answer": [
        "Famagusta or Gazimagusa",
        "or New Justiniana",
        "Siege of Famagusta",
        "Ottoman Famagusta",
        "Arsinoe before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One dissent issued in this case stated that \"Section 2 demands no such thing, and, if it did, the Constitution would not permit it.\" Edmund LaCour argued on behalf of one state for this case, while the oral arguments for the winning side were made by Deuel Ross, of the NAACP's Legal Defense Fund. Establishing that Alabama's Congressional map violated the Voting Rights Act, for ten points, what was this 2023 Supreme Court case, which required Alabama to create a second majority-minority district?",
      "answer": [
        "Allen v. Milligan or Wes Allen, Alabama Secretary of State, et al. v. Evan Milligan, et al.",
        "either underlined portion 2 2023-24 HS National History"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person's daughter, Constance, married Alan Fergant, the Duke of Brittany, while another of this person's daughters, Agatha, was betrothed to Alfonso the Sixth of Castille. Supposedly, this person's future husband dragged them off a horse by their braids and beat them after they told him a person like them could not marry a \"bastard.\" This queen, the mother of Robert Curthose [[KURT-hose]], gave her husband the ship Mora for an invasion of England. For ten points, name this woman \"of Flanders,\" the wife of William the Conqueror.",
      "answer": [
        "Matilda of Flanders",
        "Maud in place of \"Matilda\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When distinguishing two principles, this speech claimed \"whoever holds to the one must despise the other.\" This speech also claimed that the \"sacred right of self-government\" and the belief that \"all men are created equal. . .are as opposite as God and Mammon.\" Delivered in 1854 in front of a courthouse, this speech outlined its orator's opposition to popular sovereignty and the Kansas-Nebraska Act. For ten points, name this Abraham Lincoln speech, usually named for the Illinois city in which it was given.",
      "answer": "Peoria Speech"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While serving as a Union Army surgeon, this person was possibly forced to brand a deserter, an act which may have led to this person's mental instability. After committing a murder in England, this person was hospitalized, having been found innocent by reason of insanity. Portrayed by Sean Penn in the 2019 film The Professor and the Madman, this person spent many years assisting lexicographers while at the Broadmoor asylum, before Winston Churchill ordered him released in 1910. For ten points, who was this important contributor to the Oxford English Dictionary?",
        "answer": "W.C. Minor or William Chester Minor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "W.C. Minor disdained this Irish republican organization, which was founded in the U.S. by John O’Mahony and Michael Doheny and was supported by President Chester Arthur.",
        "answer": "Fenian Brotherhood"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hardresser Waller and the namesake of this event ordered the withdrawal of the Trained Bands. Richard Browne and William Waller were arrested during this event, five days prior to which, Thomas Fairfax ordered the relocation of one monarch from the Isle of Wight. A total of 45 MPs were arrested during this event, Britain's only military coup. For ten points, name this event, in which supporters of the New Model Army prevented opposing politicians from entering the House of Commons.",
        "answer": "Pride's Purge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the longest-held prisoners from Pride's Purge was William Waller, who participated in this 1639 to 1653 series of conflicts between England, Scotland, and Ireland, which included the Bishops' Wars, the English Civil Wars, and Oliver Cromwell's conquests.",
        "answer": "Wars of the Three Kingdoms"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, “Officer Bubbles” infamously threatened to arrest a woman who was blowing soap bubbles. The only police officer convicted of a crime after this event assaulted protestor Adam Nobody. Bill Blair detained hundreds of people in a film studio during this event, for which SNC-Lavalin built a five-million dollar fence around the Metro Convention Center. Police were criticized for their violent response to, for ten points, what 2010 summit in Ontario’s capital?",
        "answer": [
          "Toronto G20 summit protests",
          "2010 G20 summit protests before \"2010\" is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thirteen years before the Toronto G20 summit, the RCMP was found to have used excessive force at the 1997 APEC conference, held at which university?",
        "answer": [
          "University of British Columbia",
          "UBC"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "From 1958 to 1960, this person served as their country's prime minister after U Nu's party split in two. This leader, who promulgated a socialist constitution in 1974 after having launched a coup in 1962, established a Union Revolutionary Council that included Aung Gyi, who later criticized this general's Way to Socialism ideology. This dictator, who was opposed by protestors at Rangoon University, twice demonetized various bills and declared that \"the army shoots to kill\" during the 8888 uprising. For ten points, name this Burmese dictator.",
        "answer": [
          "Ne Win or Shu Maung",
          "or U Ne Win"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ne Win's 1962 coup occurred nearly sixty years before a 2021 coup in Myanmar deposed the government of this party, led by Aung San Suu Kyi, whose affiliated National Unity Government has since fought to retake control of the country.",
        "answer": "National League for Democracy or NLD"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person advocated a defense of traditional matrimony in an essay titled Du Mariage, and three days after succeeding Albert Sarraut [[sah-ROH]], this person's government signed the Matignon Accords into law. Recognition of shop stewards and twelve days of paid leave each year were among the stipulations of the aforementioned effort by this leader, who was imprisoned in Buchenwald on charges of treason against Vichy France. Known for his labor reforms, for ten points, who was this first Jewish prime minister of France?",
        "answer": [
          "Léon Blum or Andre Léon Blum",
          "pronunciation as ]",
          "]"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prior to his first term as prime minister, Blum was attacked politically and physically by this right- wing French movement, which favors a return to monarchical rule and is classified as anti-Semitic by hate- watch groups.",
        "answer": [
          "Action Française or AF",
          "or French Action 4 2023-24 HS National History"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This athlete is held hostage by disgruntled place kicker Ray Finkle, who repeats the words, “Laces Out” in the film Ace Ventura: Pet Detective. During the 1994 season, this person threw a touchdown on a trick play after yelling, “Clock! Clock! Clock!” and pretending to spike the ball. This man led his team to Super Bowl Nineteen but was decisively defeated by the 49ers, and this University of Pittsburgh alum threw for 5,084 yards in 1984, a record that would not be surpassed until 2011 by Drew Brees. Winning the most games of any quarterback without winning a Super Bowl, for ten points, who was this longtime player for the Miami Dolphins?",
        "answer": "Dan Marino or Daniel Constantine Marino Jr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Notre Dame alum led the team that defeated Marino’s Dolphins in Super Bowl Nineteen. This quarterback won four championships and two NFL MVPs with the 49ers and finished his career with the Kansas City Chiefs.",
        "answer": "Joe Montana or Joseph Clifford Montana Jr."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group repealed the reforms of Ephialtes [[eff-ee-AHL-tees]] and restricted political participation to the Three Thousand. After this group's extremist leader forced their rival, Theramenes [[theh-rah-MEH- nees]] to drink hemlock, it was overthrown in a revolt led by Thrasybulus [[thrah-see-BYOO-luhs]] in Piraeus. This group was installed by the navarch Lysander, and the reputation of Socrates was damaged by the fact that he taught a leader of this group, named Critias [[KRIT-ee-ahss]]. For ten points, name this group of oligarchs, who briefly ruled Athens after the Peloponnesian War.",
        "answer": "Thirty Tyrants"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The death and last words of one of the Thirty Tyrants, Theramenes [[theh-RAH-meh-nees]], is described in Hellenica, by this commander of the Ten Thousand, who gives an account of their expedition in Anabasis [[an-AH-bah-siss]].",
        "answer": [
          "Xenophon ] of Athens",
          "phonetic pronunciations"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person lends their name to a lightweight space telescope that uses a foil sheet with holes punched in it. Equations named for this scientist, who also names an elliptical region between transmitter and receiver, describe the reflection of light when it crosses different optical mediums. Known for their dioptric lens and terms such as \"linear polarization,\" for ten points, what French physicist popularized the wave theory of light over corpuscular theory?",
        "answer": [
          "Augustin-Jean Fresnel ]",
          "Fresnel Zone",
          "Fresnel Equations",
          "Fresnel Imager",
          "phonetic pronunciations"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fresnel's explanation of the diffraction effects of light utilized the formerly rejected wave theory of light developed by this Dutch physicist, perhaps best known for inventing the pendulum clock and discovering the moon Titan.",
        "answer": [
          "Christiaan Huygens ]",
          "phonetic pronunciations 5 2023-24 HS National History"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man declared the “Republic of the Floridas” after conquering Amelia Island as \"Brigadier General of the United Provinces of New Granada and Venezuela.” This man’s abandonment of troops at Porto Bello was criticized by Michael Rafter, and this man claimed that Miskito King George Frederic Augustus the First proclaimed him a cazique. The supposed leader of “Poyais,” this is, for ten points, what Scottish soldier and conman who advertised a made-up Central American country to British settlers?",
        "answer": "Gregor MacGregor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other Scottish conman pulled off a grift against Jay Gould, for which he was put on trial in 1873. The pursuit of this man by Gould and associates nearly sparked a land war between the U.S. and Canada, when the Minnesota governor mobilized thousands of volunteers for an invasion.",
        "answer": [
          "Lord Gordon-Gordon or Lord Glencairn",
          "or Herbert Hamilton"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In response to a question about this figure, one person stated that “servants never do their work when their master's hand is no longer over them.” After shedding a single tear, one man asks Eumaeus if this figure is “as fine a fellow as he looks: or if he is kept merely for show?\" This figure dies while infested with fleas and sitting atop a cow dung pile, after being the only one to recognize his master on his return to Ithaca. For ten points, name this faithful hound of Odysseus.",
        "answer": "Argos or Argus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Argus was a monster whose eyes were placed on one of these animals by his patron goddess after he was killed by Hermes.",
        "answer": "Peacock or Peafowl"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Fires",
      "prompt": "Concerning fires in US history, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "National capital, which was set ablaze in the War of 1812.",
          "answer": "Washington D.C. or District of Columbia"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York City clothing factory where many workers died trying to escape a 1911 fire.",
          "answer": "Triangle Shirtwaist Factory"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of the Confederacy and Virginia, where retreating troops burnt tobacco warehouses.",
          "answer": "Richmond"
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish immigrant whose cow was blamed for starting the Great Chicago Fire.",
          "answer": [
            "Catherine O'Leary or Catherine Donegan",
            "Mrs. O’Leary's cow"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former capital of the Hawaiian Kingdom, which was devastated by Maui’s 2023 fires.",
          "answer": [
            "Lahaina",
            "Lele"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State in which the Peshtigo fire burned much of the Door Peninsula.",
          "answer": "Wisconsin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Steamboat on which a boiler explosion and fire caused the nation’s deadliest maritime disaster in 1865.",
          "answer": "Sultana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port where a fire on the SS Grandcamp in 1947 ignited an ammonium nitrate explosion that led to other fires killing hundreds",
          "answer": "Texas City 7 2023-24 HS National History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Austria-Hungary",
      "prompt": "Concerning the dual monarchy of Austria-Hungary, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War that Austria-Hungary lost while fighting for the Central Powers in the 1910s.",
          "answer": [
            "World War One or First World War",
            "or Great War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Hungarian capital on the Danube which was consolidated in 1873.",
          "answer": [
            "Budapest",
            "pronunciations including ]"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Archduke and heir presumptive who was assassinated by Gavrilo Princip in 1914.",
          "answer": "Franz Ferdinand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruling family dynasty, which had previously ruled the Holy Roman Empire for more than three hundred years.",
          "answer": "Hapsburgs or Habsburgs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last emperor of Austria, who succeeded the throne in 1916 and died in exile in Madeira.",
          "answer": [
            "Charles the First",
            "Charles the Fourth of Hungary",
            "Charles the Third of Bohemia",
            "or Charles the Blessed",
            "Karl in place of Charles"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1920 treaty that partitioned the former Hungarian lands of the empire.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Trianon or Dictate of Trianon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Common nickname for the popular Empress who was killed by an anarchist in 1891.",
          "answer": "Sisi or Sissi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Circular grand boulevard that replaced the city walls of Vienna during nineteenth-century urban renewal.",
          "answer": [
            "Vienna Ring Road or Ringstrasse ]",
            "phonetic pronunciations 8 2023-24 HS National History"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Post-Colonial Malaysia",
      "prompt": "Concerning the post-colonial history of Malaysia, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Pandemic that indirectly led to the resignation of Muhyiddin Yassin in 2021.",
          "answer": "COVID-19 or Coronavirus 2019"
        },
        {
          "question": "City-state that was expelled in 1965.",
          "answer": "Republic of Singapore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighboring nation, whose leader, Sukarno, waged a 1960s Confrontation.",
          "answer": "Republic of Indonesia or Republik Indonesia"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in which the Chinese ethnic minority were targeted in the 13 May incident.",
          "answer": "Federal Territory of Kuala Lumpur"
        },
        {
          "question": "Towers that were the tallest buildings in the world from 1998 to 2004.",
          "answer": "Petronas Towers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bornean state, the largest in Malaysia, whose namesake \"Rangers\" became the Royal Ranger Regiment.",
          "answer": [
            "Sarawak",
            "Sarawak Rangers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Longtime opposition leader who finally became prime minister in 2022.",
          "answer": "Anwar bin Ibrahim"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebel leader of the Malayan Communist Party from 1947 to 1989.",
          "answer": [
            "Chin Peng or Ong Boon Ha",
            "in either order"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Boso Breakspeare claims this battle took place near Barranum and Brixianum. A symbolic object used at this battle was moved along the Olona River, and Charles Borromeo restored a celebration named for that item, the feast of the Carroccio. (20 pts)",
        "Despite both sides being aware of each others' presence, this battle began when two contingents of knights bumped into one another in a forest near Borsano. A victory for forced under Pope Alexander the Third, this is, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, what battle which led to the Peace of Constance and the Treaty of Venice, a 1176 defeat for Frederick Barbarossa at the hands of the Lombard League?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Legnano ]"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This philosopher's \"family rituals\" detailed the wearing of hats, and this person equated women meddling in public affairs to \"hens crowing at dawn.\" This calligrapher and poet sought to \"investigate all things to understand all things,\" but enemies said this philosopher syncretized many schools into a \"rebel clique (20 pts)",
        "of false learning.\" This person's edits and commentaries on the Four Books helped form the curriculum of the imperial civil service exam. Known for morally rebuking the Song emperor, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, who was this person, who was important in the development of neo- Confucianism?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Zhu Xi or Chu Hsi",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A work by this artist that has been reproduced on more than 20 occasions can be found beside the Quadrangle at the juncture of Chestnut and State Street in Springfield, and is called The Puritan. A sculpture honoring William Tecumseh Sherman in the Grand Army Plaza of Central Park was created by this artist, who also created (20 pts)",
        "Abraham Lincoln: The Man. The march of a volunteer infantry regiment comprised of African-American Union soldiers is depicted in a work by this man found in Boston. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, the Robert Gould Shaw Memorial was created by what sculptor of French ancestry?"
      ],
      "answer": "Augustus Saint-Gaudens"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) La Marquesa National Park commemorates this leader's victory over Torcuato Trujillo at Monte de Las Cruces. Before being executed by firing squad after the Battle of Calderon Bridge, this leader stated, \"I shall be (20 pts)",
        "remembered forever, you all will soon be forgotten.\" This leader allegedly shouted, \"Long live Ferdinand the Seventh. Long live America and death to bad government.\" The Grito de (10 pts)",
        "Dolores was a battle cry of, for ten points, what Catholic priest who led Mexico's early independence movement?"
      ],
      "answer": "Miguel Hidalgo y Costilla 10 2023-24 HS National History"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This building is named for a Kostroma monastery where a parliament announced a dynastic ascension. This building, whose site is now the location of the Church on Blood in Honor of All Saints Resplendent, was demolished in 1977 on the orders of Boris (20 pts)",
        "Yeltsin. Yakov Yurovsky oversaw the most famous act committed at this location's (10 pts)",
        "cellar by members of the Cheka. For ten points, name this merchant's residence in Yekaterinburg, where Nicholas the Second and the Romanovs were executed by the Bolsheviks in 1918."
      ],
      "answer": "Ipatiev House"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Amidst a military junta, this person announced Project Omega to bring industrial development funds for one country. To avoid copyright issues, this man added a sixth ring to the logo for the privately-owned flag carrier, (20 pts)",
        "Olympic Airlines. This man's ships often used Panamanian and Liberian flags to skirt financial and environmental regulations. Known for his affair soprano Maria Callas, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, who was this Greek shipping magnate and second husband of Jacqueline Kennedy?"
      ],
      "answer": "Aristotle Socrates Onassis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city was the site of a clock tower, which was built by Su Song and which used the first endless power-transmitting chain drive, and a handscroll painting depicting this city is titled Along the River During the Qingming Festival. Home to China's oldest Jewish community, (20 pts)",
        "this city served as the capital of the Wei state, when it was known as Daliang. In the Jingkang incident, this city fell to the Jurchen Jin dynasty, during a period in which it was named Bianjing. The former capital of the Northern Song (10 pts)",
        "Dynasty, for ten points, what is this second-largest city of modern-day Henan?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kaifeng",
        "Daliang",
        "Bianjing before mentioned",
        "Kaifeng Jews"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 18th century, this disease led a papal physician to recommended the destruction of all those exposed to it. This disease heavily affected the pastoral Nuer societies of Sudan, and during the Boer War, Arnold Theiler developed a vaccine against this disease. Described in the Roman poem De Mortibus Boum [[BOH-oom]] (20 pts)",
        "and sometimes called \"steppe murrain,\" an 1890 outbreak of this disease killed significant populations of buffalo below the Zambezi. The only disease of its kind, other than smallpox, to have been completely eradicated, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, what was this disease, known as \"cattle plague\"?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Rinderpest",
        "Cattle plague before mentioned",
        "Steppe murrain before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A New York town off the St. Lawrence was named for this person and was the site of an American blood libel, which involved the disappearance of Barbara Griffiths and the questioning of Rabbi Berel Brennglass. This leader of the victory at Saorgio received a well-known nickname after winning at Mantua. (20 pts)",
        "This general lost the First Battle of Zurich, and for losing at Sabugal in the Peninsular War, this person was replaced by Auguste de Marmont. One of the original marshals of the empire for Napoleon and known as the \"Dear Child of Victory, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, who was this French commander?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "André Masséna or Prince of Essling,",
        "Duke of Rivoli 11 2023-24 HS National History"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A manuscript by this person was found in a library at Fulham Palace and was returned to the U.S. after Frederick Temple's archbishopric gave approval. This person repeatedly traded the office of governor with Edward (20 pts)",
        "Winslow after this leader succeeded John Carver. While ill, this person was cared for by Captain Myles Standish, and this man recorded a meeting with the Pokanoket sachem (10 pts)",
        "Massasoit following his journey on the Mayflower. For ten points, name this Puritan and five- time governor of Plymouth Colony."
      ],
      "answer": "William Bradford"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The J.M. Barker Historic Reserve is home to dendroglyphs of these people on Kōpi trees. Anthropologists criticized the novel Cloud Atlas for depicting the enslavement of these people as being nearly identical to antebellum America. Tommy Solomon was generally considered to be the last (20 pts)",
        "\"full-blooded\" one of these people, who are indigenous to the Chatham Islands. The victims of a mid-19th century genocide by Māori invaders from New Zealand, having themselves originated from Māori settlers in the 16th century, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, who are these Polynesian people?"
      ],
      "answer": "Moriori"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Symonds signed articles after this battle, the eighth article of which allowed the equipping of the sloop-of-war Bonetta. Robert Abercromby led a charge to spike guns in redoubts in this battle, in which an evacuation to Gloucester Point (20 pts)",
        "was aborted. After this battle, Benjamin Lincoln was granted Charles O'Hara's sword and a band played \"The World Turn'd Upside Down.\" Fought in 1781, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, what was this last major battle of the Revolutionary War?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Yorktown or Siege of Yorktown",
        "Surrender at Yorktown",
        "German Battle 12 2023-24 HS National History"
      ]
    }
  ]
}